<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Creativity | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/creativity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T09:55:47+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Special Guest Post by Nick Hornby]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/10/22/special-guest-post-by-nick-hornby/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T14:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/10/22/special-guest-post-by-nick-hornby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This short essay by Nick Hornby is actually taken from the sleeve notes on The Gaslight Anthem&rsquo;s latest album, <em><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B007YLELM6?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=3194&amp;creative=21330&amp;creativeASIN=B007YLELM6&amp;linkCode=shr&amp;tag=dwlt-21&amp;qid=1350911867&amp;sr=8-1">Handwritten</a></em>. I&rsquo;m sharing it with you in full because I liked what it had to say: it also feels particularly relevant to my current project:</p>

<blockquote><p>It would be stupid to try and tell you that the music you&rsquo;re listening to is like nothing you&rsquo;ve ever heard before. The songs on the Gaslight Anthem&rsquo;s latest album are three or four minutes long, most of them, and they&rsquo;re played on loud electric guitars, and there are drums, and to be honest, if you haven&rsquo;t heard anything like this before, then you&rsquo;re probably listening to the wrong band anyway. What&rsquo;s great about the Gaslight Anthem is that there&rsquo;s an assumption you&rsquo;ll have heard something like this before &ndash; on the first Clash album, or on <em>Born to Run</em>, or the first Tom Petty and the Heartbreakers album, or maybe on a Little Richard record. That&rsquo;s what hooked me in. I&rsquo;ve been listening to rock'n'roll for forty years, and so maybe I&rsquo;m too old to be writing this stuff, but on the other hand, maybe I know what I&rsquo;m talking about, too: believe me, I know a lot of stuff sounds tired and derivative, and makes you feel as though rock music is exhausted. It&rsquo;s hard to find new ways to tell stories and write songs; even clothes made out of meat won&rsquo;t do you much good if your music is 1980&rsquo;s dance-pop.</p>

<p>So you have two choices. The first is this: you do something nobody&rsquo;s ever done before. You play the nose-flute underwater, put it through a computer backwards, and get a black Japanese guy to rap over the top. Or you write a novel using only consonants. Or you make a movie which nobody can see. And that&rsquo;s all cool, but nobody will want to read your second novel written using only consonants, so then you&rsquo;ll have to write one using only vowels. And the second is this: you think, write, play and sing as though you have a right to stand at the head of a long line of cool people &ndash; you recognise that the Clash and Little Richard got here first, but they&rsquo;re not around any more, so you&rsquo;re going to carry on the tradition, and you&rsquo;re going to do it in your own voice, and with as much conviction and authenticity and truth as you can muster. And if you can pull that off, you&rsquo;ll be amazed at how fresh you can sound.</p>

<p>And the Gaslight Anthem sound fresh. Anyone who has ever been frustrated by anything &ndash; a girl, a boy, a job, a self (especially that) &ndash; can listen to this music and feel understood and energised. (And if I feel energised, Lord knows what they&rsquo;re going to do to you.) And I&rsquo;m beginning to suspect that they, like, read books, too. &lsquo;Great Expectations&rsquo; &ndash; now there&rsquo;s a great title for a song. And here, &lsquo;Howl&rsquo; &ndash; there&rsquo;s another one. Rockers who read. Songwriters who are not scared to go head-to-head with everyone else in rock&rsquo;s great tradition. The Gaslight Anthem are my kind of people.</p>

<p><strong>&mdash; Nick Hornby, April 2012</strong></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
