<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Denki | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/denki/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-20T12:15:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Quarrel Day - Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/01/25/happy-quarrel-day-again/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-25T15:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/01/25/happy-quarrel-day-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.denki.co.uk/2012/01/25/quarrel-vs-the-games-industry-whos-right/">Finally</a>! <em>Quarrel</em> is here for Xbox Live Arcade!</p>

<p><blockquote><p>So who’s right then: Gamers like myself? Or the Games Industry?  Well, Wednesday January 25th 2012 is “The Day Of Reckoning”.  It’s Gamers vs The Games Industry, and one of us is definitely wrong.</p><footer><strong><a href="http://www.denki.co.uk/2012/01/25/quarrel-vs-the-games-industry-whos-right/">http://www.denki.co.uk/2012/01/25/quarrel-vs-the-games-industry-whos-right/</a> Quarrel vs The Games Industry: Who’s Right?</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>It’s true. I remember all the discussions had regarding the received wisdom that “word games don’t sell”.</p>

<p>No, badly made word games don’t sell.</p>

<p>Anyway, I for one welcome our new <a href="http://www.quarrelgame.com/">word game overlord</a>, and so should you. Buy it now, whether or not you have an Xbox. Either way, you won’t regret it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Quarrel Day!]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/08/25/happy-quarrel-day/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/08/25/happy-quarrel-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Finally. A full year, four months and three weeks since <a href="http://www.denki.co.uk/2010/04/05/black-easter-monday-at-denki-towers/">Black Easter Monday</a>, <a href="http://www.quarrelgame.com/"><em>Quarrel</em></a> has seen the light of day,
and you can now actually <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/quarrel-deluxe/id453203047?mt=8">buy it for iPhone and iPad</a> (Xbox
next, with other platforms to follow, I believe). You should do that now.</p>

<p>The first time I saw <em>Quarrel</em> was almost exactly three years ago today. I was
in the process of leaving <a href="http://www.slam-games.com">Slam</a>, and I really
wasn&rsquo;t sure what I wanted to do next. I paid a visit to
<a href="http://www.denki.co.uk/">Denki</a> to see what they were up to, since I hadn&rsquo;t
been for a while. Colin and Gary showed me a few of the pilot games they had
(just about) secured funding for, one of which was of course <em>Quarrel</em>. Every
single one blew me away, and I knew I needed to be working with them.
Thankfully for me, they agreed.</p>

<p>Things clearly didn&rsquo;t pan out exactly as we planned three years ago, but
<em>Quarrel</em> is a game that I&rsquo;m incredibly proud to have played a tiny part in
the creation of. The fact that I still love to play the game after being
involved with it for that length of time should say something about it&rsquo;s
quality and longevity. I hope you enjoy playing it as much as I do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Leaving Denki]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/04/29/on-leaving-denki/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/04/29/on-leaving-denki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was officially my last day at <a href="http://www.denki.co.uk/">Denki</a> :&ndash;(</p>

<p>At least I won&rsquo;t have the world&rsquo;s most preposterous commute anymore: four
hours a day in total. Little wonder I got so much reading done. And I won&rsquo;t
miss the guy who joined the commute at Perth, whistling like an idiot. An
idiot that doesn&rsquo;t know any tunes to whistle.</p>

<p>What I will miss is working everyday with people who give a damn, who have a
sense of purpose, ambition and no little talent. I learned a huge amount in my
18 months at Denki, all of which will serve me well in the future.</p>

<p>When I joined Denki, it became pretty clear pretty quickly that there was
something even more special than I suspected happening. That something was
channelled into <em>Quarrel</em>, a game I am incredibly proud to be associated with.
It kills me to think it might be a while before most of the people reading
this get a chance to play it.</p>

<p>But you will get to play it, I&rsquo;m certain. I don&rsquo;t know where or how or when,
but it&rsquo;ll happen.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s next for me? Right now, the only thing certain is that I&rsquo;ll continue to
be Denki&rsquo;s #1 Fan &ndash; I love what they&rsquo;re doing next (you will too), and I have
huge respect for everyone I worked with there.</p>

<p>Other than that, several things are bubbling under. My main hope is that
whatever it turns out to be, I&rsquo;ll once again be working with great colleagues,
people I can learn from and be inspired by.</p>

<p>Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
