<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 5 Things | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/5-things/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-12T14:37:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Things I'm Thinking Right Now]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/07/12/5-things-im-thinking-right-now/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/07/12/5-things-im-thinking-right-now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following on from <a href="http://www.wonderlandblog.com/wonderland/2010/07/5-things-im-thinking-right-now.html">Alice</a> and
<a href="http://www.kimpallister.com/2010/07/5-things-im-thinking-right-now.html">Kim</a>
and <a href="http://danhon.com/2010/07/12/5-things-im-thinking-right-now/">Dan</a>, here
are the five things I&rsquo;m thinking right now:</p>

<ol>
<li> The funding models for games are all there; the problem comes at the other end with actually getting something out there. Clearly this is partially about the platforms and forced scarcity, but as another example there&rsquo;s no equivalent of the film festival circuit. And even if there was, the publishers are so scared of taking a risk on anything they&rsquo;re never going to find the games equivalent of <em>Blair Witch Project</em> (insert your favourite low-budget/huge-earning here).</li>
<li> To anyone who thinks that Android is somehow &ldquo;better&rdquo; for developers, you&rsquo;ve clearly blanked out/weren&rsquo;t around for the first ten years of mobile games development.</li>
<li> There&rsquo;s so much for the games industry to learn from the TV, film, radio, music or restaurant industries that it hurts my brain. If you think otherwise, I say you&rsquo;re looking in the wrong places.</li>
<li> Nintendo do so many things so, so well, that it makes the things they do badly that much more annoying.</li>
<li> To paraphrase Greg Costikyan from a GDC rant a few years back, THE WORLD IS NOT A GIANT FUNNEL DESIGNED TO POUR MONEY INTO YOUR WALLET. Get over it.</li>
</ol>


<p>You&rsquo;ll notice none of those things involve food, but that&rsquo;s more of an
underlying constant thought rather than a specific one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
