<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nintendo | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/nintendo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-13T12:52:24+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Toys]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/04/05/making-toys/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/04/05/making-toys</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>At its heart, making toys is about using existing technology skilfully to
deliver a surprising experience. It&rsquo;s not a matter of whether or not the tech
is cutting edge, but whether or not people think it&rsquo;s fun.</p></blockquote>

<p>&mdash;<a href="http://quotabl.es/quotes/67253">Saturo Iwata, Nintendo&rsquo;s President &amp; CEO, quoted in Nintendo Magic</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Miyamoto Profiled in The New Yorker]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/12/17/miyamoto-profiled-in-the-new-yorker/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/12/17/miyamoto-profiled-in-the-new-yorker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/">The New Yorker</a> has an in-depth profile with Nintendo&rsquo;s Shigeru
Miyamoto which is worth a read (<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2010/12/20/101220fa_fact_paumgarten?currentPage=all">all-in-one page here</a>).</p>

<p>Overall, I&rsquo;d call it a positive piece, although the tone veers between
patronising and sincere. A few other things I want to comment on, in no
particular order:</p>

<blockquote><p>Fishermen have a saying, in reference to the addictive sensation of a fish
hitting your line: “The tug is the drug."</p></blockquote>

<p>So when can we expect the <em>Panorama</em> episode on fishing?</p>

<blockquote><p>this is called “gamification,” or, more gratingly, “funware”</p></blockquote>

<p>Seriously? &ldquo;Funware&rdquo; is <strong>more</strong> grating than that other word? Good grief.
I&rsquo;ll save my rant on this for another time.</p>

<blockquote><p>games are typically considered to be commercial products, rather than
creative works; consider the fact that game titles, unlike the names of, say,
movies or songs, appear in most newspapers and magazines, including this one,
un-italicized</p></blockquote>

<p>This bugs me, almost as much as it bugs me that the Guardian Gamesblog is in
the &lsquo;Technology&rsquo; section. However, this line clues us into why the industry is
approached this way:</p>

<blockquote><p>There aren’t very many video-game auteurs, but Miyamoto is one.</p></blockquote>

<p>and this quote from Miyamoto towards the end of the article nails it:</p>

<blockquote><p>“It’s becoming increasingly difficult to tell, from the looks and the play
of the games, who has created the software.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Most games companies take the Walt Disney approach, and create everything from
behind one brand. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with that. And it&rsquo;s not the oft-
lamented lack of &lsquo;auteurs&rsquo; or &lsquo;personalities&rsquo; that&rsquo;s causing the problem here
either.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a lack of <strong>distinctiveness</strong>, and not just in terms of the <a href="http://www.destructoid.com/brown-hair-and-stubble-the-new-face-of-modern-videogames-178442.phtml">central character</a>. Note that Miyamoto mentions both &lsquo;looks&rsquo; and
&lsquo;play&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The problem is that you (or, at least, I) can very rarely tell which company
is responsible for a game. Off the top of my head, if I was to do a play test
on a range of games from various creators, I think I&rsquo;d probably only be able
to identify a Valve game, a Denki game and, yes, a Nintendo game. Maybe a
PopCap game.</p>

<p>Writers, filmmakers and musicians often talk about &lsquo;finding their voice&rsquo;, the
distinctive tone or mood or themes that marks their creations out from the
hundreds of others. I think many game creators still have a way to go to find
their voice. And until games show greater diversity of theme and mood and
tone, it&rsquo;s difficult to provide a compelling argument they deserve &lsquo;creative
work&rsquo; status.</p>

<p>Anyway, asides aside, there are loads of great design tips in the article, too
many to quote here, so just go and read it. I&rsquo;ll just end with this comment
from Will Wright on Miyamoto:</p>

<blockquote><p>“He approaches the games playfully, which seems kind of obvious, but most
people don’t. And he approaches things from the players’ point of view, which
is part of his magic.”</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
