<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Awards | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/awards/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T12:14:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Sense Prevails At BAFTA]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/09/26/common-sense-prevails-at-bafta/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-26T10:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/09/26/common-sense-prevails-at-bafta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Way back in March 2011, I wrote a post over at <a href="http://scottishgames.net/">Scottish Games</a> regarding a <a href="http://scottishgames.net/2011/03/16/bafta-video-games-awards-the-missing-category/">missing category in the BAFTA Video Games Awards</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>However, I can’t help but think there’s a rather giant omission from the category list, given BAFTA’s stated aim of “developing and promoting the art forms of the moving image in the UK”: there should be a category for “Outstanding British Game“.</p></blockquote>

<p>This week, BAFTA announced that <a href="http://www.bafta.org/games/awards/categories,2469,BA.html">entries were now open for the 2013 awards</a>, along with a new category:</p>

<blockquote><p>BRITISH GAME &ndash; For the best game of the year across all genres and platforms. Creative control and development must be led by a British development studio.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hurrah! Well done BAFTA. Of course, I&rsquo;d like to claim credit for this, but I&rsquo;m just happy this particular hole has been plugged. I would still love to see an independent British game of the year prize though, <a href="http://www.dwlt.net/blog/2011/09/15/bad-gamecity-no-biscuit/">an equivalent of the Turner or Mercury prize</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bad GameCity, No Biscuit]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/09/15/bad-gamecity-no-biscuit/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/09/15/bad-gamecity-no-biscuit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>GamesIndustry.biz <a href="http://www.gamesindustry.biz/articles/2011-09-15-gamecity-launches-turner-prize-of-industry-awards">reports</a> that
<a href="http://www.gamecity.org">GameCity</a> &ldquo;have launched the <a href="http://prize.gamecity.org">GameCity Prize</a>, which it hopes will be the "Turner / Booker
/ Mercury Prize&rdquo; of the industry."</p>

<p>Brilliant &ndash; I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://scottishgames.net/2011/03/16/bafta-video-games-awards-the-missing-category/">argued before</a> that we need prizes to celebrate the
best of British talent. That&rsquo;s what the Turner (best British visual artist
under the age of 50) and Mercury (best album from the UK and Ireland) prizes
are about, and the Booker prize is for Commonwealth authors writing in
English. The jury for the prize is fantastic, and the announcement comes with
the following comment from Iain Simons, the brains behind GameCity:</p>

<blockquote><p>The GameCity Prize is about videogames gaining cultural confidence and
expressing their value in something other than financial terms. If games are
worth almost £3 billion a year in the UK &ndash; then surely they&rsquo;re worth thinking
about too.</p></blockquote>

<p>Yes, absolutely! Let&rsquo;s make a fuss and show off the best of what&rsquo;s made in the
UK! Let&rsquo;s show that we&rsquo;re not just about <em>GTA</em>.</p>

<p>Except. Except except except. The finalists announced for the GameCity prize
are from the following countries: Norway, Denmark, USA, Japan (twice), Canada
and Sweden. All worthy games, no doubt, and they&rsquo;ll all win countless awards
from other places. But they&rsquo;ll all win countless awards from other places.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tiga.org/">TIGA</a> and <a href="http://ukie.info/">UKIE</a> spend all their
time talking up the UK industry to anyone and everyone who will listen, and
yet neither BAFTA nor GameCity (arguably the only other UK organisation that
could give such a prize the credibility and platform it requires) are taking
the opportunity to celebrate the industry.</p>

<p>Or is our industry not as good as we claim?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
