<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Eating Babies | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/eating-babies/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-11T12:49:07+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EA & PopCap]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/06/23/ea-popcap/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/06/23/ea-popcap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So the rumour <em>du jour</em> of course is that EA are attempting to buy PopCap for
$1 billion (according to <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/06/22/popcap-games-to-be-acquired-for-1-billion/">TechCrunch</a>; VentureBeat also has
<a href="http://venturebeat.com/2011/06/22/popcap-sale-1-billion/">coverage</a>). I was
looking forward to PopCap going public, for a couple of reasons. First, I was
curious to see the inner workings of the company opened. Secondly, I think it
would have been a great thing for the industry in general to step eating its
own young and have a potentially hugely-powerful new pillar besides the usual
suspects.</p>

<p>Both pieces linked above have some weird bits of reporting, though:</p>

<ul>
<li>TechCrunch implies that PopCap is a &ldquo;hot gaming startup&rdquo; &ndash; whilst two paragraphs later noting that the company was founded in 2000.</li>
<li>TechCrunch claims that it would be a big deal for EA, clearly forgetting that they <a href="http://uk.gamespot.com/news/6140935/electronic-arts-buys-jamdat">paid $680mn for Jamdat</a> in 2005.</li>
<li>VentureBeat states &ldquo;EA already tried buying a social gaming company&rdquo;. Sigh. A) PopCap games are available on every platform you can think of; B) Given that PopCap are the number 3 games company on Facebook (behind Zynga, and yes, EA) according to the same report, this puts EA into a comfortable second place.</li>
<li>A later report from TechCrunch says this deal is a &ldquo;Hail Mary pass from EA to break into mobile and social gaming&rdquo;. Umm. But they&rsquo;re #2 in social, apparently, and made $242mn from mobile in FY2011, a solid 29% of their overall revenue.</li>
</ul>


<p>EA have gone on the record as saying they&rsquo;re reinventing their business as
fast as they can to take advantage of the opportunities available in digital.
PopCap built their business in digital, and have <a href="http://blog.dwlt.net/post/5768044225/popcaps-hidden-gems">a great track record of introducing successful new titles</a>.</p>

<p>EA&rsquo;s interest in PopCap is nothing to do with getting into markets they&rsquo;re
already doing quite well in. EA&rsquo;s interest is centred around PopCap&rsquo;s ability
to continually introduce new games and to make money from them. That&rsquo;s why
they bought Chillingo rather than Rovio. The fact that PopCap have also making
interesting deals in Asia can&rsquo;t have gone unnoticed either.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also some consternation over the price, and I&rsquo;ve seen various people
saying it&rsquo;s a sign of a bubble. My take is that $1bn is basically the minimum
price required to stop PopCap going public &ndash; anything less wouldn&rsquo;t be worth
their while. Given how well they manage to grow their revenue and take
advantage of new platforms, I think it may actually be a relatively cheap deal
in the long-term. PopCap may also be thinking that the impending Groupon IPO
will actually screw up their opportunity, given all the concerns about
Groupon&rsquo;s ability to actually turn a profit.</p>

<p>From EA&rsquo;s point of view, I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s a great deal. I&rsquo;d (clearly) prefer that
PopCap stayed independent. PopCap themselves provided an unofficial
politician-esque response saying that &ldquo;the company was not planning to sell to
any other company for $1 billion&rdquo; &ndash; so they might be selling for a different
price, then. We shall see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
