<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: games | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/games/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-07T15:17:28+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blizzard's Design Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2014/07/07/blizzards-design-rules/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-07T09:25:10+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2014/07/07/blizzards-design-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the news that <a href="http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2014-07-04-rob-pardos-legacy-of-steel">Rob Pardo is leaving Blizzard</a>, it reminded me I collected his &ldquo;top ten&rdquo; design rules from Blizzard
at a talk he gave at GDC 2010 and never posted them. There are probably more detailed write-ups elsewhere, but here
they are in bullet form:</p>

<ol>
<li>Gameplay First

<ul>
<li>Concentrate on the fun</li>
<li>Art, design, programming all in the service of fun</li>
<li>Design isn’t more important than others</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Easy to Learn, Difficult to Master

<ul>
<li>SImple mechanics to begin with</li>
<li>Easly play</li>
<li>Actually: easy to learn, almost impossible to master</li>
<li>Provide lots of depth</li>
<li>Trying to build depth first &ndash; harder and takes longers

<ul>
<li>Do multiplayer first, then singleplayer</li>
<li>Accessibility second</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What is the Fantasy?

<ul>
<li>What is the expectation?</li>
<li>Where is the fun in that?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make Everything Overpowered

<ul>
<li>Take everything to 11</li>
<li>Every unit, class should feel unstoppable</li>
<li>Doesn’t cost anything to make something epic</li>
<li>Applies to story and world too</li>
<li>Avoid balancing to mediocrity</li>
<li>Celebrate big differences in the game</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Concentrated Coolness

<ul>
<li>Make each feature the coolest, most concentrated expression of gameplay</li>
<li>Limited amount of complexity a player can process

<ul>
<li>eg vehicles ruined class system since you could use clas</li>
<li>StarCraft 2 has 16 units per race

<ul>
<li>Killed old units to introduce new units</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Play Don’t Tell

<ul>
<li>Play as much of the story as possible</li>
<li>Use text/voiceover/movies to enhance the story

<ul>
<li>eg 512 character limit on WoW quest descriptions</li>
<li>bad eg 2+ minute monologues in Diablo 2</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make It A Bonus

<ul>
<li>Players respond better to incentives</li>
<li>Path of least resistance should be most fun</li>
<li>Don’t fight player psychology

<ul>
<li>eg “Inspect player message”</li>
<li>Randomness &amp; progressive percentages build up (designed randomness)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Control is King

<ul>
<li>Controls should be as responsive as possible</li>
<li>Sacrifice “cool” for better control</li>
<li>Players unlikely to complain about slightly bad controls</li>
<li>Done well becomes a key skill differentiator for players</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tune It Up

<ul>
<li>Easy to do, hard to do well</li>
<li>Plan for tuning hooks</li>
<li>Know who you are tuning for and why</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Avoid the Grand Reveal

<ul>
<li>Check in often and get lots of feedback</li>
<li>Difficult to tell if an idea will work</li>
<li>Must be set up to fail</li>
<li>Iteration is critical to Blizzard dev process</li>
<li>“If you can’t build that culture, it won’t work”</li>
<li>“Want people to say ‘can you help me make this better’”</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Culture of Polish

<ul>
<li>Polish doesn’t happen at the end</li>
<li>Team gets to make their favourite game better

<ul>
<li>Make sure team loves the game</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Cross section from other teams and preview players to feed back into the game</li>
<li>Every voice matters &ndash; Don’t ship until it’s ready</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>On a related note, Pardo also mentioned something called &ldquo;Strike Teams&rdquo;, which were also mentioned by Dustin Browder
in <a href="http://www.polygon.com/2014/5/21/5723572/heroes-of-the-storm-making-of-blizzard">this interview about <em>Heroes of the Storm</em></a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We have a process here at Blizzard called a strike team where we get a bunch of people who are not on the game teams, well they&rsquo;re not on the game team making the game,&rdquo; Browder explained. Different people come into projects they&rsquo;re not a direct part of, play through the content that has been created, and give their feedback.</p>

<p>&ldquo;And it&rsquo;s the most brutally honest experience you could possibly have in your life. They&rsquo;ll just look at you point blank and say, &lsquo;Well, you&rsquo;re not gonna release this cause it sucks, right?&rsquo; I mean they&rsquo;ll just tell you whatever.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>To me, that all sounds a bit like Pixar&rsquo;s <a href="http://pixartimes.com/2014/03/12/go-inside-a-pixar-braintrust-meeting-for-upcoming-film-inside-out/">Brain Trust</a> system. (Read Ed Catmull&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00GUOEMA4/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=B00GUOEMA4&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=dwlt-21"><em>Creativity, Inc.</em></a> if you haven&rsquo;t already.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Early is too Early?]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2014/04/24/how-early-is-too-early/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-24T12:59:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2014/04/24/how-early-is-too-early</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reading <a href="http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2014-04-24-can-godus-be-fixed">&ldquo;Can Godus be fixed?&rdquo;</a> by Christian Donlan this morning on Eurogamer, a section of the last paragraph stood out:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>In truth, it&rsquo;s still hard to pin down what, if anything, 22Cans actually wants Godus to be. It&rsquo;s probably often this way in development. Maybe a team really needs to &ldquo;experiment, fail, and experiment again,&rdquo; to quote Molyneux, even if that&rsquo;s under the harsh, critical glare provided by hundreds of customers who have already paid up for the ride.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t followed Godus particularly closely (read: at all), but the above strikes me as a failure to manage expectations (on all sides). Reading the comments on the article further reinforces this, with some defending the current state of the game and others feeling like they&rsquo;ve been cheated because they already paid up for it.</p>

<p>Finding the fun, particularly on an experimental or &ldquo;reinvention&rdquo; project, can be tricky, and can take a while. Even when you have strong reference points and a fairly clear idea of what your design pillars are, it can be tricky. The problem Godus seems to be having is that they&rsquo;re building out infrastructure for the game before they&rsquo;ve figured out what core play is.</p>

<p>At <a href="http://www.gdcvault.com/play/1020034/Performative-Game-Development-The-Design">Vlambeer&rsquo;s GDC session</a> on their experience with <a href="http://nuclearthrone.com">Nuclear Throne</a> last month, Rami mentioned that at one point on the stream they&rsquo;d had to explain to viewers that they had to program what happened to bullets when they hit walls. To anyone involved in development, that seems like a silly thing to have to explain, but many people clearly have no idea how games are made.</p>

<p>Nuclear Throne looks to be a successfully managed Early Access project &ndash; it helps that Vlambeer had a game jam produced prototype (and arguably a stronger fanbase), but I also think the fact it&rsquo;s fairly clear what Nuclear Throne is trying to be helps with audience expectation (subconsciously, at least). People know what they&rsquo;re getting into and Vlambeer aren&rsquo;t building foundational game engine bits because they&rsquo;re using Game Maker. They had something that was fun from the very start of Early Access, so players can immediately see the potential and understand what the game is.</p>

<p>Godus on the other hand, has different expectations everywhere you look &ndash; some of the audience just want Populous 4, but that&rsquo;s perhaps not what 22Cans are trying to achieve. Either way, it&rsquo;s clear they&rsquo;ve let people into the process far too early &ndash; it&rsquo;s not obvious what they&rsquo;re trying to achieve with the game when you play it, and as a result journalists and players are reacting poorly to it.</p>

<p>So it seems to me that Early Access (and equivalents) can be the right thing, but only at the right time. That right time varies from project to project. It will be interesting to see how Godus fares from here on in &ndash; is the reputational damage done at this stage irreparable, or can the project be salvaged?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're Not Famous Any More]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/08/06/were-not-famous-any-more/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-06T10:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/08/06/were-not-famous-any-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Something disturbing happened at Casual Connect in Seattle. I had a conversation that went along the lines of:</p>

<blockquote><p>Me: I&rsquo;m from Ludometrics, we&rsquo;re based in Scotland.</p>

<p>Other: Scotland, cool, Is there much of a games industry there, then?</p></blockquote>

<p>If it had been a one-off, I might have brushed it off. But it wasn&rsquo;t &ndash; it happened at least twice a day for the three days of the conference. When I mentioned <em>GTA</em>, there was some vague recognition from some people that they&rsquo;d heard it was made in Scotland, once, somewhere, a while ago. And really, aside from <em>GTA</em>, what else is there you can mention?</p>

<blockquote><p>Me (looking into camera): Uh-oh.</p></blockquote>

<p>You may say that Casual Connect was the wrong conference to talk about that, given the legacy of <em>Lemmings</em>, <em>Crackdown</em> and <em>GTA</em>. <em>APB</em> hasn&rsquo;t been doing too badly either. The problem with that, though, is that virtually every company in Scotland is now working on mobile or social games &ndash; pretty much what the whole conference was centred around.</p>

<p>You may say it doesn&rsquo;t matter, nobody really cares where the games are made. That may be true on some level, but on another level &ndash; attracting (or even just retaining) talent to the country to help make those games is a fairly critical part of having an &ldquo;industry&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written about this before (in <a href="http://dwlt.net/blog/2010/09/21/the-scale-of-the-problem/">The Scale of the Problem</a>), where I lament the lack of famous games in attracting outsiders. But if other people in the industry don&rsquo;t realise we have a games industry here, we&rsquo;re in trouble my friends. I don&rsquo;t want to work in the Scottish games cottage industry.</p>

<p>So what to do? Making games that make money (as opposed to making money by making games) would be a good start. Talking about them, getting other people talking about them and telling people where they&rsquo;re made would also be good ideas.</p>

<p>Telling people where they&rsquo;re made sounds simple enough. Inspired by &ldquo;<a href="http://nytm.org/made/">Made in New York</a>&rdquo;, I&rsquo;ve created a new site which is called (amazingly), &ldquo;<a href="http://madeinscotland.co">Made in Scotland</a>&rdquo;. If you&rsquo;re making games (or any sort of tech) in Scotland, please go there and add your company to the list (it&rsquo;s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/viewform?hl=en_US&amp;formkey=dDlHNW8zSnlPYXNGX0k4Rk5XNkdGcVE6MQ">simple form</a>). Include the simple phrase &ldquo;Made in Scotland&rdquo; on your credits or options screen. People who want to or do work in games look at these screens. They&rsquo;ll see it. It seems like a small thing, but small things matter. And it&rsquo;s helped well enough for the tech scene in New York, so why not for Scotland?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Casual Connect 2012 and Selfish Creativity]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/08/03/casual-connect-2012-and-selfish-creativity/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-03T10:28:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2012/08/03/casual-connect-2012-and-selfish-creativity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I attended <a href="http://seattle.casualconnect.org/">Casual Connect 2012</a> in Seattle, where I was also speaking (slides at the end) about what I call Selfish Creativity. There was an IGDA summit on as well, although unfortunately I wasn&rsquo;t able to attend that. Thomas Bidaux of ICO has a <a href="http://www.icopartners.com/blog/archives/2982">great write up</a> on it, though, and he sums up my thoughts on the Casual Connect conference itself:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was massively biased towards user acquisition solutions and monetisation services. It makes a lot of sense as it makes the most sense for B2B companies to be exhibiting at this kind of events, but it definetely fed into the impression it is all about numbers and gaming the poor discoverability of the different ecosystems.</p></blockquote>

<p>This ties in with the one word I keep using to describe my overall feeling of the event: &lsquo;frothy&rsquo;. In other words, lots of activity on the surface, but no real structural integrity or substance. There are only so many &lsquo;payment solutions&rsquo; you can use, surely?</p>

<p>I was asked what I&rsquo;d learned from the conference. Moreso than ever, it was &ldquo;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adventures_in_the_Screen_Trade">Nobody Knows Anything</a>&rdquo;. Everyone contradicts everyone else with advice on what to do, what works on what platforms, and so on. There were a handful of good talks (there always are), notably the two from SpryFox and one from Wooga.</p>

<p>As promised, here are the slides from my presentation, &ldquo;Selfish Creativity; Or, Can Making The Game You Want To Play Lead To Success&rdquo;. It seemed to be well received by the creators in the audience, which is largely who it was aimed at. (Everything was filmed, so the video should be online by the end of August I think.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a games oriented extension of a talk I originally gave at ScotSoft 2010 (run by <a href="http://www.scotlandis.com/">ScotlandIS</a>). I&rsquo;ve found examples of it all over the place (not just in art, but also in clothing, restaurants, domestic appliances, and so on). Independently, the same idea was included as point 3 in Austin Kleon&rsquo;s &ldquo;<a href="http://www.austinkleon.com/steal/">Steal Like An Artist</a>&rdquo; list, and was also the topic of a 5-minute talk Brandon Sheffield (editor of Game Developer magazine) gave at <a href="http://gdconf.com/">GDC</a> earlier this year called &ldquo;<a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/171273/Opinion_Make_games_for_yourself__and_nobody_else.php">Make Games For Yourself</a>&rdquo; (again, unknown to me). It just proves the point really, which is that we&rsquo;re not so unique that other people won&rsquo;t want what we want.</p>

<p>TL;DR: The biggest, bestest, break-outiest things are often made by people who want the things they&rsquo;re making.</p>

<p></p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="50056752d2e765000204eb70" data-ratio="0.9481481481481482" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
