<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PopCap | dwlt.thinksOutLoud]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/categories/popcap/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T09:53:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwlt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Thomson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EA & PopCap]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/06/23/ea-popcap/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/06/23/ea-popcap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So the rumour <em>du jour</em> of course is that EA are attempting to buy PopCap for
$1 billion (according to <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/06/22/popcap-games-to-be-acquired-for-1-billion/">TechCrunch</a>; VentureBeat also has
<a href="http://venturebeat.com/2011/06/22/popcap-sale-1-billion/">coverage</a>). I was
looking forward to PopCap going public, for a couple of reasons. First, I was
curious to see the inner workings of the company opened. Secondly, I think it
would have been a great thing for the industry in general to step eating its
own young and have a potentially hugely-powerful new pillar besides the usual
suspects.</p>

<p>Both pieces linked above have some weird bits of reporting, though:</p>

<ul>
<li>TechCrunch implies that PopCap is a &ldquo;hot gaming startup&rdquo; &ndash; whilst two paragraphs later noting that the company was founded in 2000.</li>
<li>TechCrunch claims that it would be a big deal for EA, clearly forgetting that they <a href="http://uk.gamespot.com/news/6140935/electronic-arts-buys-jamdat">paid $680mn for Jamdat</a> in 2005.</li>
<li>VentureBeat states &ldquo;EA already tried buying a social gaming company&rdquo;. Sigh. A) PopCap games are available on every platform you can think of; B) Given that PopCap are the number 3 games company on Facebook (behind Zynga, and yes, EA) according to the same report, this puts EA into a comfortable second place.</li>
<li>A later report from TechCrunch says this deal is a &ldquo;Hail Mary pass from EA to break into mobile and social gaming&rdquo;. Umm. But they&rsquo;re #2 in social, apparently, and made $242mn from mobile in FY2011, a solid 29% of their overall revenue.</li>
</ul>


<p>EA have gone on the record as saying they&rsquo;re reinventing their business as
fast as they can to take advantage of the opportunities available in digital.
PopCap built their business in digital, and have <a href="http://blog.dwlt.net/post/5768044225/popcaps-hidden-gems">a great track record of introducing successful new titles</a>.</p>

<p>EA&rsquo;s interest in PopCap is nothing to do with getting into markets they&rsquo;re
already doing quite well in. EA&rsquo;s interest is centred around PopCap&rsquo;s ability
to continually introduce new games and to make money from them. That&rsquo;s why
they bought Chillingo rather than Rovio. The fact that PopCap have also making
interesting deals in Asia can&rsquo;t have gone unnoticed either.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also some consternation over the price, and I&rsquo;ve seen various people
saying it&rsquo;s a sign of a bubble. My take is that $1bn is basically the minimum
price required to stop PopCap going public &ndash; anything less wouldn&rsquo;t be worth
their while. Given how well they manage to grow their revenue and take
advantage of new platforms, I think it may actually be a relatively cheap deal
in the long-term. PopCap may also be thinking that the impending Groupon IPO
will actually screw up their opportunity, given all the concerns about
Groupon&rsquo;s ability to actually turn a profit.</p>

<p>From EA&rsquo;s point of view, I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s a great deal. I&rsquo;d (clearly) prefer that
PopCap stayed independent. PopCap themselves provided an unofficial
politician-esque response saying that &ldquo;the company was not planning to sell to
any other company for $1 billion&rdquo; &ndash; so they might be selling for a different
price, then. We shall see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PopCap's Hidden Gems]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/05/23/popcaps-hidden-gems/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/05/23/popcaps-hidden-gems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Amongst all the chatter about <a href="http://www.popcap.com/">PopCap&rsquo;s</a> <a href="http://www.techflash.com/seattle/2011/05/popcaps-plants-vs-zombies-heads-to-china.html">likely IPO</a> later this year, and the success of games such as <em>Plants vs
Zombies</em>, <em>Bejeweled</em> and <em>Peggle</em>, one thing that&rsquo;s missing is a discussion
of what underlies PopCap&rsquo;s ability to even consider an IPO: predictability.
Games are generally considered to be a hit driven business (and by extension,
a miss-led industry), so how do you mitigate those concerns? In my mind, that
comes from an aspect of PopCap that I&rsquo;ve seen zero comment about: their
ability to manage their games and brands.</p>

<p>Everyone knows about the success of <em>Bejeweled</em>, <em>Bookworm</em>, et al, but I
haven&rsquo;t seen anyone talk about their many hidden object games. How many,
exactly? Let us count them:</p>

<ul>
<li>4 in the <em>Amazing Adventures</em> series;</li>
<li>4 in the <em>Mystery P.I</em> series;</li>
<li>2 in the <em>Escape</em> series;</li>
<li><em>Vacation Quest</em> (I&rsquo;m going to guess this is the start of a new series).</li>
</ul>


<p>For those skipping ahead, that&rsquo;s 11 in total, from their current line-up of 28
PC downloadable &lsquo;favorites&rsquo; (<a href="http://www.popcap.com/allgames.php?p=pc">source</a>).</p>

<p>Given that these games can easily sell in their tens, if not hundreds, of
thousands, and that PopCap have produced multiple editions within each
franchise, something tells me they&rsquo;re not doing too badly out of these games.</p>

<p>These may not be the games that win the plaudits and awards and press, but I&rsquo;m
pretty sure they contribute to PopCap&rsquo;s bottom line in a reasonably
predictable manner. They may well be the equivalent of EA&rsquo;s annually updated
sports games, but without the massive licensing fees attached.</p>

<p>An even more undiscussed (is that possible?) aspect of this ability is the way
they take their games to as many platforms and sales channels as possible,
including boxed product at retail. From everything I&rsquo;ve heard over the years,
PopCap&rsquo;s games do phenomenally well in stores such as Wal-Mart, Target, etc.
Bear in mind that not everyone has a broadband connection, even (especially?)
not in the US, so this is still an overlooked channel for most game creators;
one that PopCap&rsquo;s games fit perfectly. I wouldn&rsquo;t be at all surprised to see
retail forming a large portion of PopCap&rsquo;s income.</p>

<p>PopCap&rsquo;s ability to nurture their franchises gives their games a far longer
shelf-life than is normally associated with the industry. The <em>Bejeweled</em>
series is the prime example of this, having sold more than 50 million copies
since it&rsquo;s debut in 2001, but they&rsquo;ve repeated the formula over and over.
They&rsquo;re amongst the best brand stewards in the industry, alongside
<a href="http://www.blizzard.com/">Blizzard</a>, <a href="http://www.nintendo.com/">Nintendo</a>,
and <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/">Valve</a>.</p>

<p>All this predictability allows PopCap to then go off and experiment with any
number of ideas. They can take an extra year to finish <em>Plants vs Zombies</em>, to
make sure it has the right level of polish. It means they can introduce new
brands, and invest enough to ensure success in the market, resulting in more
growth as they take the game to the myriad platforms that exist today.</p>

<p>To an uninformed observer like me, PopCap&rsquo;s business model seems perfectly
designed to support being a public company. Actually, scratch that; whether
public or private, they seem to have the model pretty much nailed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On PopCap's IPO]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/02/01/on-popcaps-ipo/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2011/02/01/on-popcaps-ipo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A post on <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/32755/InDepth_PopCaps_Possible_IPO__Analysts_Weigh_In.php">Gamasutra</a> (misleadingly captioned as being &lsquo;In-
Depth&rsquo;) discusses the possibility of PopCap going public later this year. I
have some &ldquo;issues&rdquo; with it.</p>

<blockquote><p>But the transition from a privately held developer/publisher into a public
one usually results in some changes to the corporate culture …</p></blockquote>

<p>Does it? <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed">Citation needed</a>, I think. I
honestly can&rsquo;t think of any comparable example. Kuju and Warthog are two
developers that went public in the UK a decade ago, but they weren&rsquo;t masters
of their own destiny. PopCap are.</p>

<p>Billy Pidgeon, senior analyst of M2 Research, then chips in:</p>

<blockquote><p>They have sort of a Disney or Nintendo thing going on in that there’s a
certain expected quality to their games. … I’d really be concerned about their
growth strategy, as it could cannibalize the elements that have made them
successful so far.</p></blockquote>

<p>Correct me if I&rsquo;m wrong, but Disney and Nintendo are both public companies,
aren&rsquo;t they? Both companies growth strategies are predicated on exactly that
&ldquo;expected quality&rdquo;. Why wouldn&rsquo;t that strategy work for PopCap?</p>

<p>As the article notes, PopCap has gone from $0 to $100 million in 10 years, and
is evidently making $1m per month just from <em>Bejeweled Blitz</em> and <em>Zuma Blitz</em>. It&rsquo;s strategy appears to be working.</p>

<blockquote><p>Pidgeon notes that despite the company’s growing reputation, it still takes
pains not to rush titles.</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;d argue that the &ldquo;company&rsquo;s growing reputation&rdquo; is exactly <em>why</em> it takes
pains not to rush titles.</p>

<p>Clearly, I have no idea if PopCap will go public or not &ndash; I believe they&rsquo;ve
been preparing for it for a couple of years, though (based on who joined their
board and the fact they started talking a lot more to the press). The success
or otherwise of the LinkedIn IPO will be just one factor.</p>

<p>All I&rsquo;ll add is that going public the week after <em>Toy Story</em> came out didn&rsquo;t
do <a href="http://www.pixar.com/">Pixar</a> any harm in terms of their culture and
growth strategy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Limit For Better]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/09/28/no-limit-for-better/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/09/28/no-limit-for-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another week, another PopCap interview, this time <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/30520/Interview_Popcaps_Johnston_On_Plants_Vs_Zombies_Tricky_XBLA_Shift.php">with Matt Johnston</a>, senior producer on <em>Plants vs Zombies</em> for XBLA
over at Gamasutra. This one generally focuses on the value of being able to
iterate repeatedly until you get it right:</p>

<blockquote><p>We spent a lot of time just trying to get [the control system] to feel right
but I think eventually we got there</p></blockquote>

<p>(Although weirdly, the next paragraph states: &ldquo;Spending a lot of time on small
elements like this is something PopCap prides itself on&rdquo; &ndash; although I&rsquo;m not
sure I&rsquo;d classify the control system a &lsquo;small element&rsquo; of a game.)</p>

<p>They bear in mind that you have to think like a player:</p>

<blockquote><p>we sat there and spent a lot of time looking at how that double sun was
going to look and animate, trying to second guess over and over and over again
how somebody who had never played PvZ or somebody who may be confused by it,
what they would think and what they would do.</p></blockquote>

<p>They obsess on details:</p>

<blockquote><p>I feel incredibly lucky to be working for a company that values those things
and shares my need to sort of exercise my OCD and go through every little
detail.</p></blockquote>

<p>Aside from iteration, they also value knowing when to stop:</p>

<blockquote><p>To be honest, getting that working and tested would have taken another six
months … I didn’t feel like it was worth [it]. … At some point every good game
developer has to decide, ‘OK, I’m actually gonna ship this game this year.’</p></blockquote>

<p>That last paragraph reminds of me of this
<a href="http://www.danpink.com/archives/2010/01/quote-of-the-day-no-limit-for-better">quote</a> from Harrison Ford:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>You keep on going until you get it as close to being right as the time and
patience of others will allow.</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>And if you read this <a href="http://www.techflash.com/seattle/2010/09/qa_popcaps_dave_roberts_on_zynga_iphone_and_more.html">interview</a> with the Dave Roberts, the
CEO of PopCap, you can see why they work like that:</p>

<blockquote><p>[W]e are pretty happy. We have never had to compromise anything about what
we believe in for great products … I think we are going to continue to build
some awesome value here, and people love the games. And we are going to keep
making great games.</p></blockquote>

<p>Lovely.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PopCap on Games You Happen To Play on Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/08/18/popcap-on-games-you-happen-to-play-on-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwlt.github.io/blog/2010/08/18/popcap-on-games-you-happen-to-play-on-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(aka what others might, on occasion, refer to as &lsquo;social games&rsquo;)</p>

<p><a href="http://gamasutra.com/view/news/29979/GDC_Europe_PopCaps_Kapalka_talks_Bejeweled_Blitz_Origins_Calls_Social_Games_A_Bit_Evil.php">Nice write-up</a> on a talk
Jason Kapalka from <a href="http://www.popcap.com/">PopCap</a> gave at GDC Europe,
centred around their experience of Bejeweled Blitz.</p>

<p>Key points:</p>

<ul>
<li>Those contests they run around the games don&rsquo;t make any difference to player numbers.</li>
<li><em>Bejeweled 2</em> just on iPhone has sold over 4,000,000 copies.</li>
<li>Resetting the high-score table (of which there is only one) once a week is better than once every two weeks.</li>
<li>Most games on Facebook are &ldquo;kind of evil&rdquo;, since they&rsquo;re trying &ldquo;any way to trick you into posting something on your wall that&rsquo;s not really even of interest to you, let alone your friends.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
